<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Popery display'd in its proper colours wherein its nonentity and nullity is demonstrated by undeniable arguments : with several remarkable passages relating to the present times : humbly offered to the honourable House of Commons / by J.S. gent.</title>
            <author>J. S., gent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62310</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S83</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9412</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11906469</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11906469</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50691</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62310)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50691)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 821:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Popery display'd in its proper colours wherein its nonentity and nullity is demonstrated by undeniable arguments : with several remarkable passages relating to the present times : humbly offered to the honourable House of Commons / by J.S. gent.</title>
                  <author>J. S., gent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. Larkin for Benjamin Harris ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Duke University Library.</note>
                  <note>The epistle dedicatory signed: J.S.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50691:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50691:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>POPERY DISPLAY'D In its Proper Colours.</p>
            <p>WHEREIN ITS <hi>Nonentity and Nullity</hi> Is Demonſtrated by UNDENIABLE ARGUMENTS. WITH SEVERAL Remarkable Paſſages Relating to the PRESENT TIMES.</p>
            <p>Humbly offered to the Honourable Houſe of Commons.</p>
            <p>By <hi>J. S.</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>G. Larkin</hi> for <hi>Benjamin Harris,</hi> at the Stationers Arms in the <hi>Piazza</hi> under the <hi>Royal Exchange.</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:50691:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50691:2"/>
            <head>To the Honourable Houſe of Commons, ASSEMBLED IN PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <p>THis Kingdom, whereof God, your King, and Countrey have made you <hi>Keepers,</hi> as well as <hi>Preſervers,</hi> cannot but ſee that nothing is wanting on <hi>Your Part.</hi> I do here but publiſh, Crier-like, the <hi>Unanimous Sence</hi> of all well-affected <hi>Proteſtants</hi> all over the World. <hi>Worthies,</hi> you are now engaged in a way of ſuch <hi>Heroick Deſigns,</hi> as <hi>Poſterity</hi> cannot but ſet the Stamp of Never-dying Honour upon You. Go on, and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt your <hi>Zeal</hi> for your <hi>Religion,</hi> and the <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and he will not fail to manifeſt Love to your Souls. Your Acts are <hi>National</hi> and <hi>Juſt;</hi> Execute <hi>Judgment,</hi> and defend the <hi>Truth:</hi> Fear not the <hi>cruel Papiſts,</hi> nor all their barbarous Adherents: And let happen what will, ſay, <hi>Malo cum Chriſto ruere, quam cum Caeſare ſtare; I had rather fall with Chriſt, then ſtand with Caeſar.</hi> God and your King hath called You for ſuch. Your <hi>Call</hi> is high, your <hi>Work</hi> is hard, your <hi>Difficulties</hi> many, yet <hi>Faith</hi> will carry You through all. You know why you have been born, not for your ſelves, but for the Benefit of many; <hi>Non ſibi ſe, ſed multorum uti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litati eſſe natum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You are our <hi>Deliverers,</hi> not only from <hi>Popiſh Idolatry</hi> and <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstitious Foppery,</hi> but alſo from ſeveral other heavy inſufferable <hi>Burthens.</hi> Believe it, moſt Noble and Renowned Worthies, all the Treaſure of this World is no way comparable to your <hi>Pious</hi> and <hi>Juſt Deſigns.</hi> Yet I hold it not onely <hi>fit,</hi> but <hi>neceſſary,</hi> that your <hi>Liberties, Laws,</hi> and <hi>Goods,</hi> ſhould ſtill be precious in your ſight; but be ſure in point of Care, to exalt the <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> (not the <hi>Pope</hi>) above your <hi>Liberties,</hi> his <hi>Goſpel</hi> above all <hi>Humane Laws</hi> and <hi>Devices,</hi> and your <hi>Religion</hi> above your <hi>Lives</hi> and <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes:</hi> Otherwiſe the <hi>Son</hi> will be <hi>angry,</hi> as well as the <hi>Father;</hi> and ſo great is <hi>the wrath of the Lamb,</hi> that the greateſt of men cannot withſtand it, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.15, 16.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:50691:3"/>
            <p>The <hi>Great Councel</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> when they ſat, exerciſed moſt part of their time in Regulating matters of Religion, and in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing of it; ſuch hath been your Endeavours, ſuch hath been your Deſires in all your Sitting. It is Ingratitude therefore in any Degrees of Men not to ſerve You. We acknowledge the Infinite Mercy of God in calling You together at this time, when no leſs then our <hi>Laws, Liberties,</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> lies at ſtake. Your Work, I confeſs, is <hi>Hard,</hi> and <hi>Great,</hi> but yet 'tis <hi>Honourable.</hi> Whoever would not <hi>endeavour</hi> to <hi>ſave</hi> his <hi>Countrey</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> is no more worthy to live in it, than the man that ſeeks the <hi>deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> thereof. The <hi>Papiſts</hi> have, dare, and will venture our ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Ruine and Deſtruction;</hi> and ſhall not we venture as far to <hi>ſave</hi> our <hi>Selves</hi> and <hi>Religion?</hi> Had men but <hi>Publick Spirits</hi> they would do it. The very <hi>Heathens</hi> have ſo minded the Publick Intereſt, as that they forgot Themſelves: <hi>Publius Decius,</hi> the <hi>Roman Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> being brought low, ruſh'd into the midſt of the <hi>Enemies,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding <hi>Safety</hi> for his <hi>Countrey, Death</hi> for <hi>Himſelf,</hi> and ſo occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned an unexpected <hi>Victory.</hi> There is no reaſon therefore that your Spirits ſhould faint, or your former Intentions ſlacken, in fear of the iſſue. You are on the Right, and on the Riſing Side; and in a Work that will Improve it ſelf: In the Work of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving our <hi>Lives, Liberties,</hi> and <hi>Religion;</hi> in the Work of <hi>Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting all His Majeſties Protestant Subjects,</hi> though the <hi>Endeavours</hi> of <hi>many</hi> are ſo mighty to oppoſe, and their <hi>Tongues</hi> ſo malignant to diſgrace it. But while You are <hi>faithful</hi> to <hi>God, Loyal</hi> to your <hi>King,</hi> and <hi>True</hi> to your <hi>Countrey,</hi> reſolve to go on in Gods Name; knowing You muſt paſs through <hi>Evil Reports,</hi> as well as <hi>Good Reports.</hi> The Lord make all <hi>Great Mountains</hi> that lie in your way, as <hi>Plains</hi> before You: Which is and ever ſhall be the Prayers of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt Obedient Servant, <hi>J. S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50691:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE NON-ENTITY or NULLITY of <hi>Popery,</hi> Demonſtrated by UNDENIABLE ARGU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENTS, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>SInce a Shadow cannot produce a Shadow, and that by reaſon of Inherency there is a neceſſary Reference in every Accident to its Subject, ſo that if the Subject be wanting, it neceſſarily followeth, that the Accident is alſo want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as loſing its Inherency, becometh nothing. This Aſſertion being as undeniable as two and two makes four, I proceed with reference to the more igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Proteſtants, not in a School dialect, (being <hi>Extra ſphaeram activitatis</hi>) but in that method, whereby the moſt Illiterate may eaſily comprehend what Popery is, whoſe high Flight and infallible Power is maintained with the outward appearance of Sanctity, and the dread of the Inquiſition, with the power and greatneſs of ſome Temporal Princes, which violently carries (where Popery Reigns) all things before it, with the impetuous ſtream of its own Torrent, teaching Sedition, Rebellion and Murder, for Apoſtolical Doctrine; having no other reality of Being to ſupport their Profeſſion (not Religion) compoſed of meer imagination and humane Invention, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to enamel and guild over their wicked Principles with many diſtorted and miſapplyed Texts of Scripture. Nevertheleſs certain it is, that whoſoever will ballance and weigh Popery with and by the Authority of Scripture, will ſoon per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, not only the fading ſplendor of Popery to reſemble the light of a Glow-worm, which the nearer one comes to it the leſſer it appears, till in the end it wholly va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth away; but a Profeſſion, moſt blaſphemouſly preſuming to Create and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nihilate two Acts proper to God alone.</p>
            <p>Some Popiſh Authors ſay, that the Prieſt by the power of Conſecration draws (I will not ſay with a Rope) or invites the Body and Blood of Chriſt from Heaven; which is as ridiculous and as impoſſible, as it is to affirm the Prieſt to have power to Create a Corporeal Body at his pleaſure, (I mean Chriſts Body) contrary to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs words of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who ſaith, <hi>The Heavens muſt contain and receive him, until the time of Reſtitution of all things, Acts</hi> 3.20. And he himſelf ſaith, <hi>I leave the World, and go to the Father, John</hi> 16. <hi>The poor ye have always with you, but me ye have not,</hi> in another place, <hi>Matth.</hi> 29.11. What a horrible and prodigious Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter is this pretended Religion, that affirms Chriſts moſt glorious Body to be at the beck of the moſt licencious Prieſt, to be given and eaten by the moſt wicked, in a hundred thouſand places at once. The ſame Apoſtle tells us, <hi>In the laſt days falſe Prophets will come, that ſhall ſay, Chriſt is here or there, and that he is in ſecret Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, Matth.</hi> 24. <hi>Believe it not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now that I may the better ſhew this, the Romiſh Faith and Divine Faith to be as incompatible as God and Nothing, I muſt (ſince the Definition of every thing is the Touchſtone wherewith men<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>try what other things can truly come within the Orb or Compaſs of the thing defined, and what not) lay down before you the Definition of Divine Faith, as the Apoſtle left it upon Record to Poſterity, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.</p>
            <p>Faith is the Subſtance of things to be hoped for, the Argument of things not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing: This Definition ſheweth, that Faith is a ſupernatural Vertue, (and not a coactive Romiſh power) and that the object thereof is that, which through its own abſtruſeneſs and ſublimity, cannot be apprehended or conceived by Natural Reaſon. To exemplifie this, Faith teacheth that in Trinity there is one peculiar Nature in three different Perſons; no mans natural Underſtanding can apprehend how this Individuality of Nature can be in three Perſons, without Diſtraction or Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplication of the Nature, becauſe every one of theſe Perſons is identified really
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:50691:4"/>and formally with this nature, in the ſtricteſt union: In like ſort, touching the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation, mans Reaſon cannot lay any true level to conceive, how one <hi>Hypoſtaſis</hi> or Perſon can be in two Natures, or how this <hi>Hypoſtaſis</hi> or Perſon is identified; for between Mans Capacity and the Nature of ſupernatural Faith, the proportion lies certainly and only in diſproportion in matters of Faith: Reaſon dictates to us to believe things above reaſon, but never againſt reaſon, as the Papiſts affirm.</p>
            <p>This Supernatural Faith hath a neceſſary reference to two things: The Firſt is <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma veritas Revelans,</hi> which is God, who revealeth all Truths and points of Faith: The Second is the Authority of the Church, to reveal all thoſe things and nothing more, which God hath revealed either by himſelf or his Apoſtles. Now let us ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine, whether theſe two points ſo neceſſary to true Faith, do accord to the Papal Faith or not: As to the Firſt, <hi>Prima veritas revelans,</hi> which is God, I freely appeal to themſelves, whether their Principles of Faith be either revealed to each particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Pope by God, or found in Scripture; (namely, every Papal Decree to be as eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential to True Divine Faith, and as neceſſary to Salvation if Revealed by God, Purgatory, Adoring and Worſhiping Images made of Gold, Silver, Stocks and Stones, in the nature of a God, praying to Saints and the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> with more zeal and eagerne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s than either to their Maker or Saviour, teaching Sedition, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, and Murder, as meritorious Acts) if neither, who will believe or ſay, but that Popery is a mere Non-Entity, or a bare Intentionality.</p>
            <p>As to the Second Point, which is the Authority of the Church, in propounding to her Children the things by God revealed, we know and affirm, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> dare not publickly own to have received either from God or Scripture (though daily practiſed by Her and her Emiſſaries) the aforeſaid Principles; the verity of this we have not only from Scripture, but from the ingenious Confeſſions of their moſt Learned and Ancient Authors. Mark withal, how theſe falſe Prophers, to ſerve as certain Veils or Curtains, to hide their helliſh and wicked Principles from the eyes of the Ignorant, do forbid under pain of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication the Reading of holy Scripture, the infallible Guide to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Thus far to demonſtrate, both from the definition of Faith ſet down by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and from the Points neceſſarily concurring for the cauſing not only of true Faith, but of Salvation; that Popery, in regard of its wanting theſe two neceſſary Points, is but an abſolute Nullity of Faith and Religion.</p>
            <p>For every thing that hath a real Exiſtence or Being, may have its Nature ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicated by the Definition of it, which conſiſteth of two parts, that is <hi>Genus</hi> and <hi>Differentia:</hi> The <hi>Genus</hi> doth comprehend the Eſſence of the Thing defined, the <hi>Differentia</hi> doth more particularly Conſtitute the thing defined, and diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſheth it from all other things. For Example, A Man is defined to be <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimal Rationale,</hi> a Creature enjoying Reaſon; the word <hi>Animal</hi> demonſtrates the Eſſence of Man; <hi>Rationale,</hi> that is, Rationality, doth Conſtitute man in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition, and maketh him to differ from all other ſublunary Creatures. A De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition extendeth it ſelf not only to the Exiſtence, or want of Exiſtence in things corporeal or material, but alſo to the Being or not Being in things ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culative and immaterial; I mean in Do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rines and other ſuch Theories of the Underſtanding. Now Popery, which in it ſelf truly implyeth an abſolute Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, cannot be thus defined, and is undenyably compounded of ſeveral Contradictories, and oppoſite Doctrines and Tenets, can have no being but intentionally, for whatſoever implyeth a Contradiction, ſuppoſeth a Being and a not Being of a thing, and all at one and the ſame time: From, whence this Abſurdity muſt needs follow, that is, if ſuch a thing could be, then could a thing be whoſe Being ſhould conſiſt in a not Being, conſequently a Nullity.</p>
            <p>This is Popery.</p>
            <p>But to Contract this Point, I will particularly inſiſt (as moſt conducing to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:50691:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Subject in hand, and the time that Proteſtants can now afford or ſet apart to read, there being ſo many Pamphlets abroad) that the Reader may eaſily diſcern what mutual Recrimination, and what irreconciliable Repugnancy there is between the Papiſts themſelves and this, even in matters of the greateſt and higheſt conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence; witneſs the many Books they have written, and the acerbity of Style one againſt another, even intimating thereby, that the different Doctrines differently maintained by them, were truly Contradictories, containing and defending diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Tenets, ſo repugnant and contradictory one to another, that even by the Law and Nature of Contradictories, the one ſide muſt ever want a real and ſubſiſting Being. Several Books written and allowed of in <hi>Rome,</hi> wherein many Principles of Faith, and the civil Power of Magiſtrates were controverted, with many Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Decrees, were by order of the Biſhops and Councils of <hi>France,</hi> burned by the Hangmans hand; they alſo decreed, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> do vary from the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Doctrine of the Scriptures, and yet now adays all are good Chriſtians and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts that oppoſe Proteſtancy, or cut Proteſtants Throats.</p>
            <p>Now I cloſe up this point, referring to the judgment of the learned Reader, how deadly Popery is wounded, not only by the Pen of Popery, but alſo by its Helliſh and daily Practice. For the nature of true Faith (and true Chriſtianity) exacteth, that it ſhould be complete, entire, and perfect in it ſelf, like unto an Action mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally vertuous, which is accompliſhed by the acceſs of all due conducing Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, but vitiated through the abſence but of any one. Many other contradicto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Points by them maintained as Evangelical and true Popery, I here pretermit till better opportunity, and aſſure the Reader that Popery is no true Faith, but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect thereof an abſolute Irreality, or an intentional Name or Word.</p>
            <p>Thus much for the Nullity of Popery, and we ſay with the Prophet <hi>David, Thou haſt ſaved us from our Enemies, and haſt put them to ſhame that hated us: In God we boaſt all the day long, and will praiſe thy Name for ever, Pſal.</hi> 44.7, 8. We are not only to praiſe him with high praiſes, with one heart and voice, and with the beſt of our Members, but alſo to purſue and ſtrive to ſet up his Name far above all bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and praiſe, by praiſing him perpetually, by perpetuating his praiſes unto Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; and by laying up ſuch a ſtock and ſuch a method of Praiſe, as may be of great uſe and importance to our poſterity, when they ſhall both ſee and hear what great things the Lord of hoſts hath done for this our Church and Kingdom. Gods wonderful Providence towards the ſafety of this Nation, and in keeping out Popiſh Idolatry, will undoubtedly, by ſome good pious man, be treaſured up in one Volume, and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to Poſterity, as a laſting Monument of Gods praiſe and Providence, as a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of Thankfulneſs from Generation to Generation, and as a true Record of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Villany, that our Poſterity may ſay with the Faithful in former times, <hi>We have heard with our Ears, our Fathers have told us what work thou didſt in their days, in the times of old, Pſal.</hi> 44.1.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Now as to the Remarkable Paſſages.</head>
               <p>NEver was Action more conducive to the ſafety of this great Metropolis, the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>London,</hi> and the whole Kingdom, than to look back and remind the woful days of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> and the burning of <hi>London</hi> to aſhes, the bloody and fatal ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects (never to be forgotten) of theſe two, are to be attributed only to Popery, and to that Man of ſin that exalts himſelf above all that is called God, (the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi>): wherefore 'tis the hopes of <hi>A. P.</hi> a Member of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> whoſe Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy and Rites are worthy of admiration, that all Proteſtants of what perſwaſion or intereſt ſoever, unanimouſly conclude and agree to aboliſh Popery, as well Root as Branch. Several have propoſed their Expedients for the aboliſhing of this helliſh and venemous Root Popery; therefore I hope I may take the ſame liberty, and throw in my Mite alſo, being thereunto induced by the affection I bear my King and Country, as in duty bound.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:50691:5"/>
               <p>The preſent State and the great fear of the Nation, of being overrun with Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and ſo brought to Beggery and Slavery, exacts an Angelical Spirit which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears the ſame as well in the dark as in the light, <hi>(qui vult capere capiat)</hi> and a Hercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lean Courage which is never to be daunted, and this (attributed to <hi>Engliſh men</hi> formerly) that you act upon all neceſſary occaſions unanimouſly, in the preſervation of your King, your Religion, and Property, like good Chriſtians and <hi>Engliſh men.</hi> I ſay <hi>Engliſh men,</hi> becauſe <hi>Engliſh men,</hi> when they embrace Popery and reject Proteſtancy, they loſe their courage, (like our Engliſh Maſtiffs when ſent beyond the Seas) and in lieu thereof receive all manner of Villany. This needs no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proof, than the Reading the Tranſactions of the laſt time when Popery Reign'd amongſt us; then our Divines were butchered by the Name of <hi>Heretick Dogs,</hi> our Houſes plundered, our Wives and Daughters raviſhed, our Churches erected for the true worſhip of God, abuſed, and converted into the Temples or Places of Idolatry and Superſtition, to the great diſhonour of Chriſt and ſcandal of Religion: Nay many of our Laity were torn to pieces, and tied to a Stake in the midſt of flames at <hi>Smithfield,</hi> and other places. Can we then be ſo infatuated as to expect any bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter entertainment than our Predeceſſors? No certainly: For beſides that dreadful and barbarous entertainment which our Predeceſſors had from that Helliſh and Popiſh power, we ſee and will mind that our apparent ruin is not only aimed at, and that without mercy, but that we are only ſecured during the life of one man, the Life of his Sacred Majeſty, whom God long continue with this happy Parliament, whoſe Intereſts and ours are the ſame, and ſo united, that our Reſolutions are the ſame. If the Plot takes effect (I mean the killing of the King) or the Plotters make a head, as in all probability they will, (being diſappointed in taking away the Kings life) and if in the interval of Parliaments they happen to take off the King, we have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more to do than to deſtroy the whole Popiſh blood, who with all ingratitude and baſeneſs attempted the Life of our Prince and all his Proteſtant Subjects.</p>
               <p>Here we are to obſerve and believe, that there is no ſuch thing as an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt who is not in the Plot, at leaſt in his good wiſhes; and that it is a Maxim (nay a Principle of Faith) with all Papiſts, and eſpecially with ſuch as are in power, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to keep their words or promiſes with Hereticks: (Some may here object, that ſome do keep their promiſes with Hereticks: I anſwer, that it is for Intereſt or Fear, and not out of Conſcience;) Therefore whoſoever credits a Papiſt, be he never ſo plauſible in his Religion and Converſation, is never to be pitied when thus precau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned. Obſerve likewiſe, how the <hi>French</hi> King, a Popiſh King, levyes Arbitrary Taxes at his pleaſure, and impoſes ſeveral other Tyrannical Oppreſſions at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. Now leſt any ſhould be ignorant, that any ſuch like Diſtemper may not be much eaſier prevented at firſt, than when it has once got a head; it's ſufficient to tell you, that the Pope and Papiſts are your mortal Enemies, and would fain Reign and Domineer over this Kingdom in the ſame nature as the <hi>French</hi> King doth in <hi>France.</hi> Theſe are the men who exclaim againſt our Parliaments proceedings, and prevail with many others, not much better than themſelves, in relation to the Plot: theſe are the men that endeavour to amuſe as well his Sacred Majeſty as his good people; alledging that there is no Plot, but rather 40, and 41.</p>
               <p>I muſt acknowledge that there is ſome coherence between 40 and 41, and this preſent time; for as well then as now, the Popiſh and <hi>French</hi> Faction were the chief, nay the only Incendiaries which promoted and cauſed all the miſchief of 40 and 41, which is well known to many, and eſpecially in the Rebellion of <hi>Ireland,</hi> where ſo many thouſands of Proteſtants were killed by (a counterfeit) Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Here they intended no leſs, but God fruſtrated their deſign, and inſnared them in their own Net. The Papiſts in 40 and 41 as well as now, have allured many lukewarm Proteſtants to their aſſiſtance, which in great part ſupported their helliſh machinations on foot ever ſince Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s days. Methinks this and this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent helliſh Plot, ſhould be a ſufficient caution to all Proteſtants, and chiefly to all ſuch as are in Power, not only to avoid and ſhun the Company of Papiſts, but alſo to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horr the very Name and Intereſt of a Papiſt, and ſay with the Holy Patriarch, <hi>O my Soul, come not thou into their Secrets, unto their Aſſembly my Honour be not thou united, Gen.</hi> 49.6. I would have all true Proteſtants ſay thus, and profeſs with the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50691:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>Prophet <hi>David</hi> to Almighty God, that <hi>He was a Companion to all them that fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, and of them that kept his Precepts, Pſal.</hi> 119.63. What credit then can a Proteſtant propoſe to himſelf in keeping company with a Papiſt, much leſs in promoting or maintaining his Intereſt? For no Proteſtant can be ſo infatua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted (if not deeply concern'd in the Plot, or very ignorant) to believe that a Papiſt fears God, or keeps his Precepts: But ſince they are not all <hi>Iſrael</hi> which are of <hi>Iſrael</hi> (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid) nor all Proteſtants that come to Church, as I wiſh they were, and there really appear what they are as well internal as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal, and not lye ſheltering themſelves within the pale of our Church, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the wings of Proteſtants promote the Popiſh Intereſt: But they are eaſily known, for what our Saviour ſaid of the Wolves in Sheeps cloathing, is eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally true; <hi>By their Fruits ye may know them, Matth.</hi> 7.16. Having this infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible mark and Divine Caution, beſides ſeveral late paſt Paſſages (if well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved,) nothing more doth concern all Proteſtants, than to United and Act as the Proteſtants did in Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> time: The Papiſts forelaw they could do nothing, unleſs they could cut her off, therefore all their Plots and helliſh Deſigns were calculated againſt her life as they are now againſt his preſent Majeſty (whom God long preſerve:) The Proteſtants foreſaw that there was no end of their Plots and helliſh Deſigns, till they would have cut her off, and conſequently extirpate the Proteſtant Religion, if by ſome extraordinary means they did not prevent it; upon which they did by an univerſal and unanimous Aſſent, enter into an Aſſociation, by which they mutually promiſed to each other to repair to their Arms, and ſtand by and aſſiſt each other with their Lives and Fortunes in theſe three caſes. 1. In caſe of the Queens death. 2. In caſe of a Foreign Invaſion. 3. In caſe of any Popiſh Inſurrection. Beſides, they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged themſelves one to another, whenever the Queen fell by any untimely end, they would revenge her death upon the Papiſts. This immediately put a ſtop to all their Plots and Deſigns againſt her; for when they ſaw the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants were unanimouſly agreed on that point, (which is to be wiſhed for now) and that taking away the Queens Life, was their total Ruine and Deſtruction, the Papiſts had ſoon done with their (Plottings: This, never to be forgotten Act of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Proteſtants, and in an interval of Parliament, was ſo univerſally approved of, that ſhe her ſelf in the next Parliament confirmed it, and made it Law.</p>
               <p>Now it's to be admired, how one Proteſtant calls another Rogue and Rebel, for ſubſcribing or promoting a harmleſs Petition for the Sitting of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to redreſs the Grievances of the Nation: The Parliament having already ſtigmatized theſe horrid Abhorrers and ſtrange kind of Proteſtants, never to be forgotten, and not worth my while to decipher their Popiſhly affected Crime, it being daily to be ſeen and read in their faces: I only tell them, that I am ſorry that ſuch are permitted amongſt Proteſtants, for they can make as good Papiſts ſuppoſing Intereſt, as they are now Proteſtants.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the men that proſecute Proteſtant Diſſenters, and if Popery were turned Trump, would willingly deſtroy all that would not conform to their Livery and Superſtitious Levies, as they did in the days of Queen <hi>Mary;</hi> for it is very well known, that the profeſſed Papiſts were no more able then than they are now to deſtroy they Proteſtants: No, it was the Proteſtant Abhorrers, that wicked Crew, the worſt wretches, that turned Papiſts, and ſpilt the blood of all true Proteſtants, as they thirſt to do with ours now: Of ſuch Abhorrers as theſe, I would have all honeſt minded men and true Proteſtants, to ſhun and avoid their Company, and ſcorn their Society, with a juſter indignation than a known profeſſed Papiſt; from a known Papiſt you can guard your ſelf, but from theſe miſcreant Wretches you cannot; for they walk and converſe with you as Friends, like deceitful and bloody men, and lye in the boſom of the Church till they ſting her to Death, as they did in the <hi>Marian</hi> Days.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:50691:6"/>
               <p>Now is the time, not to Diſpute or debate much about a Plot (which is ſo evidently demonſtrated and confeſſed by all, except thoſe that are therein concerned) but to Act, and that with ſpeed and univerſal Aſſent againſt Popery, and all its Adherents; otherwiſe <hi>England</hi>'s Religion, Liberty and Property is loſt. In this our Gracious King neither is or will be wanting, as he aſſured this preſent Parliament in his Royal Speech to them. Popery and all its profeſſors,
<list>
                     <item>1. Are Enemies to God by their ſetting up and worſhiping of Idols as God, contrary to his expreſs Command: (Truth hates Competitors.)</item>
                     <item>2. To Chriſt by their new found Mediators, and eſpecially the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> whom they ſtyle <hi>Salvatrix Peccatorum.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. To Scripture, by their many corrupt Traditions and humane Inventions, in impoſing a belief upon all their Proſelytes, not only to deny their Reaſon, but all their other Senſes, to the great detriment of their Souls, and the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour of their God and Saviour.</item>
                     <item>4. To all Oppoſers by Fire and Faggot.</item>
                     <item>5. To all Government that will not ſubject to their Antichriſtian and Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious power, by Plots, Aſſaſſinations, Poyſoning and horrid Maſſacres; theſe to be Popery's uſual and common ſteps to worldly Advancement, to its ſupport and propagating, is notoriouſly known, eſpecially to this Nation, whom Popery (the common Enemy of Mankind) hath ſo often attempted, our ruine, and at ſeveral times hath been at the very point of effecting it; has once more with that great violence attempted our utter ruine, which I hope will be ſo order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as to be their laſt Attempt; and if not, we are not to be pitied. The great Undertakers and Encouragers of this Helliſh Plot, ſome have had their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts, ſome are fled from Juſtice, and promiſe themſelves good ſucceſs in their Deſign; not becauſe of the many thouſands of Maſſes that are daily ſaid all over the Papal World, for the proſperity of their Deſign; but becauſe they have Friends in Diſguiſe amongſt us, as they moſt impudently aſſert, in our Courts, in our Armies, in our Navyes, (which I would not have believed, had not ſome late paſſages happened: Their Deſign is not to convert, but to kill, burn, and plunder; it being juſt and meritorious to extirpate He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks Root and Branch.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>But Bleſſed, be God, their chief Aim, the Killing of the King, whoſe only life is our ſafery, has failed, and ſo confounded them, that they afterwards reſolved to ſurprize us and make a Night-work of us, as they did in <hi>France, Piedmont,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> in thoſe moſt bloody and barbarous Maſſacres of poor innocent Proteſtants; but God notwithſtanding the multitude of our ſins hath hitherto preſerved us (though deſign'd many a time to a total deſtruction) and diſcovered this impious and helliſh Conſpiracy, to the great confuſion and ſhame of the Conſpirators; he has alſo beaten up our Quarters, and given us the Alarm, if we will take it, as we ought, all things conſidered: We have been told, that not only our Forts, our Militia, but <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> were at a Papiſts beck.</p>
               <p>Beſides the great danger of being ſtabbed as we walk in the Streets, and of being burned as we ſleep in our houſes; witneſs that horrid murder of Sir <hi>Edmondbury Godfrey,</hi> the barbarous Aſſaſſination of Juſtice <hi>Arnold,</hi> and the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Fire of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Southwark,</hi> to which let us add, their unanimous aſſent and deſign in extirpating all Hereticks (as they term them) root and branch, by cutting their Throats, having no other way to propagate their Profeſſion, that has nothing of Religion but the Name: therefore Gratitude nor Countries ſake reſtrains not men of this ſtamp, their Principles know no Kindred, no Love, no Obedience, no Obligation to a Heretick but through blood, as the Murther of Sir <hi>E. G.</hi> can teſtifie. O wonderful! that ever ſuppoſed Chriſtians ſhould be ſo much the Children of the Devil; as firſt to Murder, then charge it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the innocent ſoul Murdered, as the Papiſts moſt Impudently did and do; in him all Proteſtants were Maſſacred, no man is ſure of his life a day or night; the choice is only what death we ſhall dye, whether be Stabbed, Strangled, Burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:50691:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>or Poyſoned; this Conſternation, in ſecurity, and danger of our Lives, muſt needs obſtruct not only all Commerce betwixt man and man, but alſo deter Officers of Juſtice from their Duty and Obligation, and in fine diſſolve all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ſociety, and reduce the world into miſery.</p>
               <p>How much then doth it concern all Proteſtants, nor only with unfeigned Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance to turn to the Lord, and beg of him that theſe Conſpirators ſhould be either Confounded and inſnared in their own Nets, or diverted from their helliſh deſigns: Not that this is ſufficient, but we, ought as in duty bound, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve our King, whom the Conſpirators aſſert (bleſſed be God) is not for their turn; and make our humble Supplication to this worthy and <hi>Engliſh</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, to Vote an Adreſſe to the King, to Baniſh all Papiſts and all Popiſhly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, as well out of his Army and Navy, as the Cities of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter;</hi> whoſe Villiany and Cruelty, one would think, ſufficiently rendered them as uncapable of ſerving in our Armies, as in keeping humane and Common ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety with Proteſtants, whileſt poor and Innocent and diſſenting Proteſtants are daily moleſted and pilledged for the ſake of their peaceable Conſciences, and Popiſh Rebels ſheltering themſelves under our Roof: is this to Maintain the Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion? No certainly, it is inſupportable.</p>
               <p>Therefore call for the Conſpirators, look throughly and ſtrictly into their helliſh Actions; <hi>fiat juſtitia:</hi> fear nor favour no man, but fear Cod; do what you do as in his preſence, to whom you muſt render an account; nay, or every idle word; 'tis the chief and moſt applaudable Action of your Life, to di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>charge your Truſt; that is, (if you will quit your ſelves like Men and good Proteſtants) preſerve the Being, Liberties and religion of thoſe who have intruſted you, by throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out Popery after the Bill, the only Tormentor and Plague of this Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: as you deſire to ſee God in his Glory, and ſecure your ſelves from Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, Tyranny and Slavery, neglect not this Opportunity which God has ſo wonderfully caſt into your hands unexpected; be not Deſpi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers of his Care and Providence over you, neither be you careleſs or fearfull of Improving and Shewing your Power: Now is the time; for had they you (or ever will) at the ſame advantage, you nor yours ſhould not long continue; therefore what before you would ſcarcely have done, is now become your Duty: Let not the Life of that Grand Traytor and Popiſh Courtly Secretary, who Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terouſly communicated the ſecrets of our King and Countrey to all Popiſh Courts in <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> nor the Lives of five or ſix bigotted Jeſuits, paſs as ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction for this horrid and (never to be forgotten) Helliſh Conſpiracy: Not that I deſire more Blood, but Juſtice, Security, and future ſafety as well for our Poſterity as for our ſelves; otherwiſe it may be truly ſaid of us, <hi>They ſaw and would not ſee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You know that Popery marks all Proteſtants of what perſwaſion ſoever out for the ſame end, and eſteems them as one body of Hereticks, equally deſerving the Slaughter, as <hi>Bellermine</hi> affirms: All Hereticks are to be deſtroyed Root and Branch, if it can poſſibly be done: <hi>De Laicis, lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 22.</p>
               <p>Beſides, all Hereticks are ſolemnly Curſed once a Year in <hi>Rome,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Papiſts in the ſeveral Kingdoms where the Proteſtant Religion rules, are not only diſcharged from all Allegiance to their Prince, but all are obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the ſtricteſt bond of Conſcience, and under the penalty of the utmoſt hazard of their Souls, to depoſe ſuch Heretical Princes; and that they are ſo far from being Guilty of Murder if they kill any of them, as <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the Third, Pope, ſaith, that they are bound to exterminate all Hereticks, as they would be eſteemed Chriſtians themſelves; <hi>Mariana</hi> ſaith, When the Common-wealth cannot otherwiſe ſecure and preſerve its own peace and ſafety, it may by a right inherent in it ſelf, declare the King to be the common Enemy, and then deſtroy him with the Sword. <hi>Leſhius</hi> ſaith, that ſuch a Prince ought to be depoſed, and therupon it may be lawfull to attempt any thing againſt his Perſon. Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the fifth did not only Excommunicate and Damn Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> and all her Proteſtant Subjects, but alſo Curſed all the Papiſts that ſhould give any Obedience to her, or her Laws. All this one would think, ſhould not only
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:50691:7"/>rouſe us to Self-defence, Brotherly love and Union betwixt all Proteſtants, but alſo to determine, that whoſoever oppoſed ſuch, may be Judged to love Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry better than Proteſtancy, conſequently an Enemy to the King, the Proteſtant Religion and the Government.</p>
               <p>In reference to Self-defence, after a true Union is once ſetled among all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, it's moſt neceſſary that our Militia Officers, all ſtanding Officers, Judges, and all Juſtices of the Peace ſhould be ſtrictly examined, whether they be men Popiſhly affected or not: if popiſhly affected, they are the moſt dangerous to be truſted, and the ready way to introduce Popery: the firſt have our Lives in their hands, and may cut our Throats at will; the ſecond will never put the Penal Laws in Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (if not againſt Proteſtant Diſſenters) which is no leſs than to cheat the Government, and Invalidate the King and his Laws. Popery, and men Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhly affected, (or in <hi>Maſquerade</hi>) fear nothing more than ſuch ſtrict En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry: Be not ſlow in this, (we will never leave you) for ſuch ever ſince the Reformation, were our greateſt Enemies, and chief Fomentors of Plots and Conſpiracies. If you read of the Maſſacre of <hi>Paris, Piedmont</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> with the Tranſactions acted upon this our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Stage within theſe few years, you will find this confirmed and much more, (too long here to inſert) to your great ſatisfaction, and the Confuſion of many great Courtiers, who for Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt have betrayed God and their Countrey: wherefore, if now after all theſe great Diſcoveries, Juſtice were not done on this wicked and bloody Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who ſince they could not cut off the King by their Buliies, nor the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies of the Nation by a Meal-tub Plot, intended no leſs than a publick Maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre, had not the Wiſdom of God, the Courage of the Parliament, who ever loved and honoured their King, their Countrey, and the Proteſtant Religion more than their Lives and Fortunes, detected their Villany, and put themſelves with undaunted Courage between them, his Majeſties Life and the Proteſtant Religion, to the great Terror and Confuſion of all Papiſts in the World:</p>
               <p>A Generation who put themſelves into various Forms and Shapes, though never ſo Monſtrous, to carry on the good Cauſe, and all tending to one and the ſelf ſame end, the Deſtruction of the Proteſtant Religion; though the Villany and Debauchery of ſome is ſuch, as to reckon every one either a Presbyterian or a Fanatick that appears more than ordinary active againſt theſe Papiſts: There is a duty and a great obligation incumbent upon all true lovers of the Proteſtant Religion, to Unite and Joyn with one Voice; and obſerve the words of <hi>Abraham</hi> to <hi>Lot, Let there be no ſtrife, I pray thee, between me and thee, for we are Brethren, Gen.</hi> 13.8. Are we not Brethren? Undoubtedly the Papiſts Rage is equal againſt us, why ſhould we Quarell then with our Brethren, who the Papiſts would deſtroy becauſe they are Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants? therefore we ought to own and preſerve them as ſuch, and to give them all the Demonſtration that can be, both of love and of laying aſide all Prejudices and Animoſities that either Papiſt or Devil can ſuggeſt to perſecute our Brethren, who truly labour in the Vineyard, and Exhort to give <hi>Caeſar</hi> his due, and to ſubmit to every Ordinance of man for the Lords ſake, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be to the King as Supream, or unto Governors, as unto them that are ſent by him for the puniſhment of evil doers, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13.</p>
               <p>This infallibly will put a ſtop to all Popiſh Operations, though their Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies are of ſuch a reaching magnitude, as if they were laid in the very depths of Hell, as undoubtedly they were.</p>
               <p>The Romiſh Emiſſaries here in <hi>England</hi> doe not only operate by diſtilling Notions in Religion, but alſo in affairs of State (which is well known in all Courts in <hi>Chriſtendom</hi>) and chiefly in the Court of <hi>England:</hi> witneſs the laſt unhappy War, that happened between the King and the Parliament, they were the chief cauſe and Fomentors of it, notwithſtanding their great and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Loyalty to King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt, which they ſo confidently Boaſt of; nothing will appear more ridiculous, if you conſider,</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:50691:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> their commencing that bloudy Rebellion in <hi>Ireland,</hi> where ſo many. Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of His Majeſties <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Subjects were butchered, for which they pretended to have a Commiſſion under the <hi>Great Seal:</hi> this cauſed and encreaſed the <hi>Fear</hi> and <hi>Jealouſie</hi> of all the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in <hi>England</hi> (as well it might) that the like might be deſigned againſt themſelves: they alſo renounced all Allegiance to His Majeſty, and owned the <hi>Pope</hi> as their Supream King. This obliged the Parliament to requeſt of the King, ſuch and ſuch things as they thought moſt convenient and moſt conducing to his ſafety, their own and the Nations. The King finding it not fit or neceſſary to grant all that they demanded, proved to be one matter, and in part cauſe of the laſt War, and the fatal ill conſequences of it; in which the <hi>Papiſts</hi> at firſt were very a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive for the King, well knowing that the foundation and only cauſe of the War, was only in oppoſition to their Party, ſo that their Loyalty and Service to the King was meerly in their own defence, not out of any true Loyalty or Principles of Religion; for their Religion commands and teaches the contrary, as their practices, as well then as now, confirms, and leaves no colour of denial; ſo that I much fear that they will, as well now, as then, run the hazard of a War, thinking thereby to eſtabliſh their Foppery.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Their Fidelity and Loyalty to the King in the latter end of the War; when many of them revolted, and took part with <hi>Oliver;</hi> others laid down their Arms, made their peace with <hi>Oliver,</hi> and told the King they would never fight a ſtroke for him or his, is very well known. When the War was ended, and the King o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome in the Field, it is evident that the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and <hi>Prieſts</hi> ſtirred up thoſe Sons of <hi>Belial</hi> to Murder His Sacred Majeſty; the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and <hi>Prieſts</hi> did alſo endeavour to encline the People to a <hi>Common-Wealth,</hi> and was at the ſame time very earneſt with <hi>Cromwel</hi> to accept of the Crown, and offered him all Obedience and Allegiance ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable, but <hi>Cromwel</hi> knowing, full-well, that their Religion taught them, that no way was to be refuſed or ſlighted, though never ſo unlawful, whereby they might promote or advance the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſlighted them, and kept them out of all places of Truſt, and ſo much under, that they could never attempt any thing againſt him, or at leaſt, they would not, though a Traytor to His King.</p>
               <p>Now their Loyalty to this preſent King, evidently appears to the World in their many Attempts upon his Sacred Life; in their Helliſh Deſigns; in ſubverting his Government, burning his Cities, and murdering his Subjects, and all this according to the Principles of their Religion: What Villanies will not theſe Monſters at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt? what Intereſt or Right will not they invade? what ſo Sacred that they will not violate? what can limit them if they find opportunity to accompliſh their deſire? Miſerable muſt that Nation be that will be ſubject to ſuch inconveniences and poyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Poſitions, not only deſtructive to Publick Safety, but alſo to the Honour of God and the Glory of his Church: In declaring this, I do, in effect, alſo declare, That what has been theſe many years, and now is acting among the <hi>Papiſts, is an old Play newly revived.</hi> What the <hi>Papiſts</hi> did in the late times was laid upon the <hi>Phana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques,</hi> the like was to have been done at this time: Juſt before the diſcovery of Dr. <hi>Oates</hi> they ſeized upon one Mr. <hi>Claypole</hi> and impriſoned him, for having (as they pretended) a deſign to Murder His Sacred Majeſty, thinking thereby to convince the World, that Mr. <hi>Claypole,</hi> and ſome of the old Party had a Conſpiracy to take away the Kings Life, that in the mean while, the <hi>Papiſts</hi> themſelves might with ſafety do it, and lay it upon the <hi>Nonconformiſts,</hi> who in all truth and ſincerity own their ſafety and peace to His Majeſty only; for when Dr. <hi>Oates</hi> firſt diſcovered the <hi>Plot,</hi> Mr, <hi>Claypole</hi> was not only releaſed, and his pretended Crime forgotten, but the Parties, called <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> were the moſt active, and are to this day, both in the preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of His Majeſties Life, and the further diſcovery of the Plot, as is too apparent: Such another Sham-Plot as this, undoubtedly was the laſt Rebellion in <hi>Scotland</hi> fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented and moved by <hi>Papiſts,</hi> diſguiſed Prieſts and Emiſſaries, who make it their on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly buſineſs, firſt to inſinuate to the Common People ſome Erronious Principles in Religion, who, as ſoon as they are tainted by thoſe Deluſions and poyſonous Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that are daily diſtilled by diſguiſed Prieſts amongſt them, thinks themſelves illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated by divine Light, and ſo led captive, being never well principled in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to believe any thing for Religion from theſe diſguiſed Prieſts, who aſſures them
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:50691:8"/>that the Biſhops are <hi>Papiſts,</hi> that the King of <hi>England</hi> is a Heretick, and not their true King, and that he hath broken the Covenant both before God and Man, and that they ought not to obey nor obſerve his Commands, nor the Commands of any appointed by him; but at all times oppoſe him and his, and defend themſelves and the <hi>Kirk,</hi> as they hope to ſee the Kingdom of Heaven.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Theſe <hi>diſguiſed Prieſts</hi> poſſeſs the Common People with a Belief, <hi>That they are bound by the Laws of God and Man to unite and take Arms againſt any that op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs them:</hi> and all this, to encourage the poor People to Mutiny amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and ſo give it the name of a <hi>Presbyterian Plot.</hi> But if the <hi>laſt Rebellion</hi> were fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented and encouraged by <hi>Presbyterians</hi> or <hi>Fanaticks,</hi> how comes it to paſs that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Officers and Souldiers who were disbanded a little before this Rebellion, <hi>had notice to keep their Horſes, and to be in readineſs, for that they would ſoon have occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to uſe them?</hi> And ſo it happened, for within a fortnight after the <hi>Disbanding,</hi> the Rebellion broke out in <hi>Scotland.</hi> Certainly, no man can imagine that the <hi>Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> or <hi>Fanaticks</hi> of <hi>Scotland</hi> did ever ſend word to theſe Officers and Souldiers, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to keep their Horſes, or be in readineſs; ſure it is then, that they muſt have it from the <hi>fomenters,</hi> the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> for to them only it was advantagious, in reſpect it had the name of a <hi>Presbyterian Plot:</hi> for thereby they hoped to bury their own <hi>Popiſh Plot,</hi> and to have all <hi>diſſenting Proteſtants diſarmed,</hi> the chief thing at that time aim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at, and a matter worthy all true <hi>Engliſhmens</hi> Obſervation.</p>
               <p>And alſo, That reſpect and kind uſage the <hi>French</hi> King and his <hi>Catholicks</hi> treated His <hi>preſent</hi> Majeſty with, when they <hi>baniſhed him their Countrey,</hi> notwithſtanding, even to the <hi>Destruction of our ſelves,</hi> the <hi>Protestant Religion,</hi> as well as <hi>home,</hi> as <hi>abroad,</hi> have we eſpouſed the <hi>French</hi> King and his <hi>Catholicks</hi> quarrel? But why? His <hi>ſlighting</hi> and <hi>baniſhing</hi> our <hi>gracious King,</hi> his <hi>Popery, Foppery, Idolatry</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> could nor ought not to be the Motive; much leſs his <hi>tranſmitting ſeveral Summs of Money to</hi> Coleman <hi>to bribe our Parliament:</hi> What then? I know not, but the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> (if not the <hi>Reader</hi>) can. Yet I cannot but remind you, how we have with all eagerneſs imaginable, <hi>aſſiſted the</hi> French <hi>in their Conqueſts,</hi> as if we had deſired no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more than <hi>Arbitrary</hi> and <hi>Popiſh Government,</hi> two things inconſiſtent with the Laws of the Nation, and the Humour of all true <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> who can expect no more mercy from the <hi>French,</hi> or a <hi>Popiſh Succeſſor,</hi> than a <hi>Mouſe</hi> from a <hi>Cat;</hi> wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the <hi>Marian</hi> days: <hi>for the greater number of Hereticks they kill, the greater is their Merit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let theſe things be conſidered before it be too late, for a <hi>Popiſh Succeſſor</hi> holds it as a <hi>Duty incumbent,</hi> and counts it <hi>his Glory,</hi> and the <hi>greateſt Glory, to destroy Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiſm,</hi> as <hi>peſtilent Hereſie;</hi> for his <hi>Religion</hi> teaches not only, <hi>that it is a deadly crime to favour Hereticks;</hi> but alſo, <hi>That if a Prince ſhould ſolemnly engage his Faith, and give as much Security as any can give by Oath, yet when in the Throne, he is bound to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy all Hereticks:</hi> for the greater the <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> the greater will the <hi>Value</hi> and <hi>Merit</hi> of it be. So that the greater any wickedneſs is, or the more prodigiouſly Bloody and Inhumane it is, the more powerful Motive the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> hath for its encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Thus the Spirit of <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Deluſion</hi> would fain perſwade us, <hi>That the moſt horrid and barbarous Deſign that ever the Devils helped any of their inſtruments to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive, is ſo tranſcendently both meritorious and juſt:</hi> This is not a private Spirit or a private Opinion, but that by which the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> is generally inſpired. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, when I think of this, and how faithful and ſerviceable we have been to the <hi>French</hi> King in his <hi>Late Wars,</hi> and altogether unkind and deſtructive to thoſe of our own <hi>Religion,</hi> as well abroad as at home, to the great <hi>Wonder</hi> and <hi>Amazement</hi> of the moſt part of the <hi>World,</hi> I cannot but aſcribe our preſent Troubles and Calamities, rather to our undertaking to advance the <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Greatneſs</hi> (than either to <hi>Folly, Reaſon</hi> or <hi>good-Nature</hi>) of him, I mean the <hi>French</hi> King, who <hi>endeavoured by all Arts and Stratagems imaginable, to ſubdue us to Arbitrary Power, Popiſh Idolatry and Foppery;</hi> to compaſs this the eaſier, <hi>he bribed and paid Penſions to ſeveral about our Courts,</hi> as <hi>Lewis</hi> the Eleventh did to all Perſons whom he thought had any power with King <hi>Edward;</hi> he was eaſily prevailed with to do any thing, being a <hi>Papiſt;</hi> but <hi>bleſſed be God,</hi> our preſent King, <hi>whom God preſerve,</hi> gave the <hi>World</hi> ſufficient Teſtimony, as well while he was amongſt them, as ſince His Bleſſed <hi>Restauration,</hi> of His <hi>contemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:50691:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>and <hi>abhorring</hi> their <hi>Tyrannical Power,</hi> their <hi>Superſtitious Idolatry</hi> and <hi>Fopperies;</hi> for he knows full-well, and cannot but be ſatisfied, <hi>That no Religion or Government can be ſo much for His Majeſties Advantage, both in reſpect of Eternity, and this Worlds en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment, as this Religion which is now profeſſed</hi> (Proteſtancy) <hi>in England.</hi> Although His Majeſty would by <hi>Popery</hi> be made <hi>Abſolute</hi> over his <hi>Subjects,</hi> yet His <hi>Slavery</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſo <hi>Tyrannical a power,</hi> would be ſo <hi>great</hi> and ſo <hi>inſupportable,</hi> that as well <hi>Liberty</hi> as his <hi>Revenues,</hi> would be much leſs than now (<hi>Peter-pence</hi> muſt be paid, <hi>Licences</hi> and <hi>Indulgences</hi> for this, and that, muſt be had, and paid for; eſpecially in caſe of <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi>) Whoever pleaſes to read our <hi>Chronicles,</hi> will ſoon perceive, <hi>That no Servants have been</hi> (ſo much kept under) <hi>greater Slaves to their Masters, than many of our</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh <hi>Kings were to the Pope;</hi> and thoſe who were above his <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> the <hi>Romiſh Church</hi> ever found ſome way or other to cut him off, either by ſetting his People againſt him, as they did by King <hi>John;</hi> or by ſome <hi>Popiſh Poyſon,</hi> or by ſome bloudy <hi>Godfrey Dagger.</hi> king <hi>Edgar</hi> for his <hi>Incontinency</hi> was <hi>enjoyned</hi> by <hi>Dunſtan</hi> Abbot of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury, not to wear his Crown for Seven Years,</hi> to which he was forced to ſubmit. To Expiate the Murder of <hi>Thomas Becket,</hi> King <hi>Henry</hi> the Second (though <hi>unknown</hi> to him, <hi>committed by his Courtiers</hi>) was forced <hi>to walk bare-footed three Miles to viſit his Shrine, and then to receive ſeven Laſhes from the Monks.</hi> King <hi>John</hi> for oppoſing <hi>Pope Innocent</hi> the III. was (after interdicting the <hi>Kingdom</hi> for <hi>Six Years</hi> and <hi>Three Months</hi>) forced <hi>to render his Crown to</hi> Pandulphus <hi>the Popes Legate, for ſome time;</hi> yet all this did not ſatisfie the <hi>Ambitious Prelates</hi> Malice, but <hi>he cauſed him to be poyſoned in</hi> Swinſted-Abbey, by one <hi>Simon</hi> a <hi>Monk.</hi> Be pleaſed now to <hi>obſerve, That in the time of</hi> Popery <hi>Princes lived not ſo peaceably, nor with that ſafety, as now they do.</hi> As for <hi>Example:</hi> The Emperor <hi>Henry</hi> the VII was <hi>Poyſoned in receiving the Popiſh Sacrament from his Prieſt:</hi> This <hi>preſent Emperour,</hi> about ſome <hi>nine Years</hi> ago, was like to be <hi>Poyſoned</hi> by his <hi>own Chaplain,</hi> who when he was giving the <hi>Eucharist</hi> to his <hi>Master</hi> the <hi>Emperour,</hi> his <hi>hands</hi> and <hi>body</hi> trembled in ſo unheard-of-a-manner, that the <hi>Emperour</hi> being thereat ſomewhat amazed, asked, <hi>What ailed him?</hi> the <hi>Priest not having power to ſpeak, ſtood ſtill like a Stock;</hi> ſome of the <hi>Courtiers</hi> obſerving all, came up towards the <hi>Priest,</hi> and forced him to eat his <hi>Superstitious God,</hi> upon which <hi>he dyed upon the place. Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the III of <hi>France</hi> was <hi>Stabbed</hi> by <hi>Clement</hi> the <hi>Monk. Henry</hi> the IV of <hi>France</hi> was <hi>Stabbed</hi> by <hi>Ravilliac a Jeſuit.</hi> But to come home, (though I could give an <hi>Hundred o-Examples of this Nature,</hi> and of the <hi>Popes</hi> themſelves, who often <hi>poyſoned</hi> ſeveral of their <hi>Cardinals.</hi>) I ſay, that betwixt the time of <hi>William the Conqueror,</hi> and the <hi>begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> of this our <hi>Bleſſed Reformation,</hi> Seven of our Kings <hi>were murthered, Viz.</hi> King <hi>John, Richard</hi> I. <hi>Richard</hi> II. <hi>Edward</hi> II. <hi>Edward</hi> V. <hi>Henry</hi> VI. and <hi>Richard</hi> III. Now, <hi>What intereſt Princes can propoſe to Themſelves or their Subjects, by introducing or favouring Popery,</hi> I know not; unleſs they deſire to be <hi>thus Murthered</hi> or <hi>Governed</hi> by the <hi>Pope,</hi> till <hi>destroyed</hi> by his <hi>Caterpillars:</hi> From which, <hi>Good Lord (and the best of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments) deliver us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I muſt confeſs, that ſome <hi>Princes</hi> are of <hi>ſo good a nature,</hi> and of <hi>ſo great Clemency,</hi> that it makes them not only <hi>not to expect,</hi> but alſo, <hi>not to think</hi> that any of <hi>thoſe</hi> to whom they have been both <hi>kind</hi> and <hi>very indulgent,</hi> ſhould any way prove <hi>treacherous</hi> and <hi>falſe</hi> to them; but <hi>Experience</hi> for undoubtedly ſuch, as having more <hi>eaſie</hi> and <hi>free Acceſs</hi> to their <hi>Prince,</hi> and conſequently, more <hi>opportunities</hi> to <hi>betray</hi> their <hi>Prince</hi> then <hi>others,</hi> are the Men over whom the <hi>Prince</hi> and the <hi>Whole Nation</hi> ought to have <hi>a more wary and ſtedfaſt, Eye,</hi> for all <hi>Plots</hi> and <hi>Conſpiracies</hi> are <hi>generally begun by ſuch as are moſt familiar with their Prince, and moſt in his Favour:</hi> whoſever pleaſes to read <hi>Hiſtory</hi> will find, <hi>that many Princes have been deſtroyed by their greateſt Favourites, and too too often, by their impatient Heirs; even ſometimes by Their Own</hi> Sons <hi>and</hi> Brothers. Did not <hi>Cain</hi> kill <hi>Abel?</hi> And was not <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſold into <hi>Egypt</hi> by <hi>his own</hi> Brothers? Had not <hi>Agrippina</hi> her Sir <hi>G.W.</hi> by whoſe <hi>power</hi> and <hi>advice</hi> ſhe <hi>poyſoned</hi> her <hi>Husband Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius?</hi> was ſhe not her ſelf afterwards <hi>killed</hi> by her <hi>own Son Nero?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now if a little <hi>love,</hi> or a little <hi>animoſity,</hi> or a <hi>little intereſt in the World,</hi> makes the <hi>Wife kill her Husband,</hi> makes a <hi>Brother kill a Brother,</hi> and the <hi>Son</hi> the <hi>Father,</hi> what will not the intereſt of this <hi>World,</hi> and the <hi>enjoyment</hi> of <hi>Heaven</hi> do, which is far more <hi>prevalent,</hi> and daily <hi>promiſed to any that will kill and deſtroy the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pholder or Supporter of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:50691:9"/>Hereſie</hi> (the <hi>Popes</hi> own terms) I cannot therefore <hi>believe</hi> that a <hi>Prince</hi> (nay any one) can think himſelf <hi>ſecure,</hi> whilſt he has a <hi>Popiſh Heir</hi> or <hi>Relation,</hi> within ſight. That <hi>Popery</hi> was to be <hi>introduced</hi> by the <hi>Kings Death,</hi> is paſt <hi>denial;</hi> and how any one could be privy to <hi>This,</hi> and not to the <hi>Means</hi> to <hi>Effect it,</hi> I leave the <hi>Reader</hi> to judge.</p>
               <p>That the <hi>Papists</hi> had <hi>a Deſign, not onely to introduce Popery, but alſo to murther the King,</hi> what is more certain? How many <hi>Princes</hi> have been <hi>murthered</hi> by <hi>Popiſh Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies?</hi> How many <hi>Helliſh Attempts</hi> have they made upon our <hi>Kings,</hi> and to <hi>intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce Popery</hi> into <hi>this Nation?</hi> Why then are we ſo <hi>ſlow</hi> in bringing theſe <hi>Vipers</hi> to <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dign puniſhment according to Law?</hi> Our <hi>neglect</hi> and <hi>tardineſs</hi> herein, is the greateſt <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement</hi> imaginable to the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> as their ſeveral and frequent <hi>Attempts</hi> demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, notwithſtanding their being ſo often <hi>fruſtrated</hi> and <hi>defeated</hi> in their <hi>Helliſh Machinations</hi> and <hi>Horrid Deſigns.</hi> The <hi>introducing of Popery</hi> ſhould not ſeem to us <hi>improbable;</hi> for their <hi>Principles</hi> are ſtill and ever will be the <hi>ſame,</hi> their <hi>Hopes</hi> are as great <hi>now<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> as <hi>ever;</hi> they gain <hi>three Plotterr,</hi> for every <hi>one</hi> they loſe, and ſuch as <hi>Staf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> procured (<hi>Goal-Birds, Pick-pockets, Horſe-ſtealers, Cheats, Popiſh John,</hi> and <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates,</hi> all little to his credit) to <hi>confront</hi> the <hi>Kings Evidence,</hi> who had ſeveral <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> both of <hi>Worth</hi> and <hi>Quality,</hi> to <hi>confirm their Evidence:</hi> To all which, I was <hi>Eye-Witneſs</hi> at the <hi>Tryal</hi> of <hi>Stafford:</hi> though not at his <hi>Firſt Tryal,</hi> for he was <hi>before</hi> tried for his <hi>Life</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> for <hi>Sodomy,</hi> and there <hi>condemned to die,</hi> had not <hi>Money</hi> and <hi>Friends</hi> procured his <hi>Pardon,</hi> as I hope <hi>neither</hi> will now; he deſerving rather to be <hi>Rack'd to Death,</hi> then to have the favour of <hi>Cutting off his Head;</hi> notwithſtanding his <hi>great Aſſeverations, That he never ſo much as thought of killing the King:</hi> A Popiſh <hi>Equivocation!</hi> For he knew the <hi>King</hi> was <hi>Excommunicated</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> and conſequently <hi>No King in his Opinion.</hi> And further, to murder one that bears the Name of a <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical King,</hi> eſpecially where there is a <hi>Popiſh Succeſſor</hi>) is a moſt <hi>meritorious Act;</hi> nay, the <hi>greateſt of all Merits,</hi> by reaſon of the <hi>vaſt advantage</hi> that will thereby a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crue to the <hi>Popiſh Religion;</hi> not doubting but that the <hi>reſt</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom</hi> will <hi>(Regis ad exemplum)</hi> ſoon after turn <hi>Papiſts.</hi> This, and the <hi>wonderful Diſcovery</hi> of this <hi>Plot,</hi> our <hi>Deliverance</hi> from utter <hi>Ruine,</hi> (wherein undoubtedly <hi>Gods</hi> great <hi>Providence</hi> appeared very remarkable) and the many and great <hi>Diſcouragements</hi> the <hi>Kings Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> and this <hi>Plot</hi> met withall, (but from <hi>whom?</hi> from thoſe certainly that <hi>are in the Plot,</hi> or that <hi>wiſh</hi> it may take <hi>effect,</hi> whoſe <hi>Principles</hi> we know are ſufficient to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take any <hi>Villany</hi>) may well aſſure us, That all the <hi>favour</hi> His <hi>preſent Majeſty</hi> (whom God long preſerve) can ſhew them, will not ſatisfie that great <hi>Expectation</hi> which they have from a <hi>Popiſh Succeſſor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe <hi>Obſervations</hi> (moſt worthy <hi>Parliament,</hi> and true <hi>Engliſh Patriots</hi>) I have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed to offer to your <hi>Conſiderations:</hi> Firſt, In reſpect you are the only Perſons ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of Preſerving the <hi>King,</hi> our <hi>Lives, Liberties,</hi> and <hi>Estates.</hi> Secondly, You are the Perſons, if ever the <hi>King</hi> ſhould be taken off by <hi>violence,</hi> (which God in his infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite mercy prevent) that muſt <hi>Revenge his Death;</hi> the <hi>whole Kingdom</hi> is <hi>ready,</hi> and <hi>will aſſist You.</hi> God preſerve the <hi>King,</hi> and give a happy <hi>Concluſion</hi> to all your <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultations,</hi> which is an ever ſhall be the conſtant and hearty Prayer of</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your moſt Obedient, and moſt Faithful Servant, <hi>J. S.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
               <pb facs="tcp:50691:9"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
